<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Henk-Jan van den Ham on Henk-Jan van den Ham</title>
    <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Henk-Jan van den Ham on Henk-Jan van den Ham</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Henk-Jan van den Ham</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity measures for antibodies: the adapted Shannon diversity index (ASDI)</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2017-11-20-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2017-11-20-diversity/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The diversity index is based on diversity concepts from ecology, where it is used to estimate the diversity of plant and animal life. You can think of the diversity index as a way to perform a weighted count of species. If you would like to compare the species diversity in different habitats, there are several ways of doing that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can count the number of different species present (but sensitive to &amp;lsquo;single&amp;rsquo; animals that are just &amp;lsquo;visiting&amp;rsquo; a habitat)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use the number of animals of which there are at least an &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; number (but difficult to determine &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;, e.g., 5 elephants is deemed more important for diversity than 5 ants)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a weighted average whereby animals are given more importance if there is many of them (that is the one we&amp;rsquo;re using!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diversity-measures-101&#34;&gt;Diversity measures 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different diversity measures. Each of them has a different range and all their values have different interpretations. To make life easy, these values can be represented as the number of responses of equal magnitude so as to provide an intuitive measure that everyone may understand. So a diversity of 5 means: &lt;em&gt;a diversity comparable to having 5 equally abundant species&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a highly cited (and highly recommended!) paper, &lt;a href=&#34;10.1111/j.2006.0030-1299.14714.x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;L. Jost, Oikos 2006&lt;/a&gt;) shows that many diversity measures map onto one another if you introduce a weighting factor that tunes the relative contribution of high- and low-abundant species to the final estimate of diversity. The final form of diversity equation looks scary, but is quite easy to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://henkjanvdh.github.io/img/diversityExample.png&#34; alt=&#34;Diversity measure example&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $D$ is the diversity measure of order $q$, $S$ is the number of species, and $p_i$ the proportion of animals from a specific species, expressed as a fraction.  Depending on how you weigh high-abundant vs low-abundant species (that would be parameter $q$), you obtain a different estimate of diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;interpretation&lt;/em&gt; of this index is diversity equivalent to that number of equally abundent species. For instance, a diversity of 3 means: 3 equally abundent species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adaptation-to-antibody-measurements&#34;&gt;Adaptation to antibody measurements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The index is adapted to be used for evaluating antibody measurements, i.e., fluorescence. To quantify diversity of responses, this index can be used. However, to down-weigh the influence of unprotective responses (i.e., those with a low fluorescence value), we include a parameter that sets the minimal level of what is considered an effective response: an &lt;em&gt;offset&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;anchor&lt;/em&gt; value to distinguish between background and real responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anchor value is taken along when the fractions of species are calculated. Please note that the anchor is not a cutoff, because the values below it are given less weight - but still taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://henkjanvdh.github.io/img/diversityAntigenArray.png&#34; alt=&#34;Diversity measure example for antigen arrays&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/freidl_sr16/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;our paper in Scientific Reports&lt;/a&gt; for more details. &lt;a href=&#34;https://images.nature.com/original/nature-assets/srep/2016/160208/srep20385/extref/srep20385-s1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Supplementary material S3&lt;/a&gt; contains the full derivation of the adapted index.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DC vaccination for HIV</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/project/hiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2017 11:23:31 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/project/hiv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To treat HIV-infected individuals, one approach is &lt;em&gt;therapeutic vaccination&lt;/em&gt; that aims to induce durable immunity by reactivating the individual&amp;rsquo;s immune system to HIV. Ideally, this would lead to viral control without taking combined anti-retroviral therapy (cART).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project, we examine several cohorts with -omics technology to try and understand the effect that these DC vaccinations have on vaccinated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcriptomic Analyses Reveal Differential Gene Expression of Immune and Cell Death Pathways in the Brains of Mice Infected with West Nile Virus and Chikungunya Virus</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/lim_fm17/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/lim_fm17/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of differentially expressed peptides in high-throughput proteomics data</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vanooijen_bb17/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vanooijen_bb17/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wat doet een virus?</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2016-11-21-virgo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2016-11-21-virgo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Wat gebeurt er wanneer je geinfecteerd wordt door een virus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De afgelopen jaren heb ik geprobeerd deze vraag te beantwoorden in het kader van het &lt;a href=&#34;http://virgo.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;VIRGO project&lt;/a&gt;. De focus van dit project was om door middel van nieuwe &lt;em&gt;genomics&lt;/em&gt;-technologie virusinfecties in gastheren te bestuderen en bestrijden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KennisLink heeft een deel van dit onderzoek voor het voetlicht gebracht door onderzoekers te interviewen. Tijdens een van deze interviews heb ik verteld over ons onderzoek om &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nemokennislink.nl/publicaties/een-kakofonie-van-genactiviteit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;knokkelkoorts beter te begrijpen&lt;/a&gt;. Mijn collega Victor heeft verteld over ons werk &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nemokennislink.nl/publicaties/ziekenhuis-of-niet-je-genen-bepalen-het?q=virgo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;om de uitkomst van RSV infectie in jonge kinderen beter te voorspellen&lt;/a&gt;. De vraag was hier: welke kinderen een ernstige vorm van RSV zullen ontwikkelen en welke niet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;brochure&#34;&gt;Brochure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Een deel van het werk binnen het VIRGO project, waaronder de bovenstaande artikelen, is opgenomen in een &lt;a href=&#34;http://assets.kennislink.nl/system/files/000/239/550/original/VIRGO_boekje-dig_NED.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;brochure over het VIRGO project&lt;/a&gt; en maken deel uit van het KennisLink-thema &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nemokennislink.nl/thema/virussen-te-lijf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Virussen te lijf&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changes in heterosubtypic antibody responses during the first year of the 2009 A(H1N1) influenza pandemic</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/freidl_sr16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/freidl_sr16/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcriptome assists prognosis of disease severity in respiratory syncytial virus infected infants</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/jong_sr16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/jong_sr16/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DC immunotherapy in HIV-1 infection induces a major blood transcriptome shift</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/degoede_v15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/degoede_v15/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time since Onset of Disease and Individual Clinical Markers Associate with Transcriptional Changes in Uncomplicated Dengue</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_pntd15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_pntd15/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A better understanding of helper T cell differentiation using mathematical modelling and bioinformatics</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/thesis_2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/thesis_2010/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
