<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Henk-Jan van den Ham on Henk-Jan van den Ham</title>
    <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Henk-Jan van den Ham on Henk-Jan van den Ham</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Henk-Jan van den Ham</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>qPCR analysis</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2017-12-11-qpcr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2017-12-11-qpcr/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This post does a step-by-step analysis of quantitative PCR data. It includes compensation for amplification efficiency and the incorporation of both single and multiple loading controls. If you like derivations, keep reading; if you&amp;rsquo;d rather skip the mathematics, go to the &lt;a href=&#34;#ddct&#34;&gt;final forms&lt;/a&gt;. Excel implementations are provided at the &lt;a href=&#34;#excel&#34;&gt;end&lt;/a&gt; of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ct-values-101&#34;&gt;Ct values 101&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;qPCR yields Ct-values, which is the number of amplification cycles needed before a fluorescent signal is detected. Every cycle, the amount of nucleic material doubles, up to a maximum, which is effectively the limit of detection. The relationship between the number of cycles ($Ct$) and the amount of amplified nucleic material ($C_n$) is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ C_n = Cq \cdot a^n $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $a$ is the PCR amplification efficiency (which is \( \approx 2 \), $n$ is the number of cycles, and $Cq$ is the initial amount of material. With qPCR, we measure $n$ when $C_n$ reaches a specific fixed value $K$:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ Cq \cdot a^{Ct} = K $$
$$ Cq = \frac{K}{a^{Ct}}$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;qPCR data is often presented is the form of a Ct value. Effectively, this is expression data on a $log_a$ scale:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ Ct = log_a\left(\frac{K}{Cq}\right) = -log_a\left(\frac{Cq}{K}\right) $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accounting-for-qpcr-amplification-efficiency&#34;&gt;Accounting for qPCR amplification efficiency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When interpreting Ct values, we need to take some technical points into account. The qPCR reaction efficiency need not be perfect, which means that the number of Ct cycles is overestimated. This will in turn cause differences in outcomes, in particular when the data are generated on different plates or with different batches of reagents. Using a calibration setup (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www3.appliedbiosystems.com/cms/groups/mcb_marketing/documents/generaldocuments/cms_040377.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taqman efficiency calculation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), the efficiency can be measured and incorporated into the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the equality $log_y(x) = \frac{log_z(x)}{log_z(y)}$, we take change the Ct values to a base 2 logarithm for simplicity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ Ct_{norm} = -log_2(a) \cdot log_2{\left(\frac{Cq}{K}\right)} = log_2(a) \cdot Ct$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accounting-for-sample-loading-delta-ct&#34;&gt;Accounting for sample loading ($- \Delta Ct$)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we need to take into account differences in sample content and loading. This is done by selecting a reference or &amp;lsquo;household&amp;rsquo; gene that is assumed to have the same concentration in all samples. Therefore, results are given as $\Delta Ct$ relative to the household gene. To make the results more intuitive by having an increasing value representing increasing expression, the $-\Delta Ct$ is typically presented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ -\Delta Ct_t = log_2(a_r) \cdot Ct_r - log_2(a_t) \cdot Ct_t $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $a_r$ and $Ct_r$ refer to the reference (i.e., household), and $a_t$ and $Ct_t$ refer to the target gene values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;readout-changes-relative-to-control-delta-delta-ct&#34;&gt;Readout: Changes relative to control ($-\Delta\Delta Ct$)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have properly calibrated and normalized the values, we can compare treatment to control. Since we are then taking differences between two ($-\Delta Ct$) values, the resulting value is typically refered to as ($-\Delta\Delta Ct$):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ -\Delta\Delta Ct = \Delta Ct_m  - \Delta Ct_t $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we start from the non-calibrated Ct values of the mock ($Ct_m$), target ($Ct_t$) and references ($Ct_r$ and $Ct_s$), this is the expression for a normalized $-\Delta\Delta Ct_n$:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ -\Delta\Delta Ct = \log_2 \left( a_m \right) \cdot Ct_m - \log_2 \left( a_l \right) \cdot Ct_l - \log_2 \left(a_t\right) \cdot Ct_t - \log_2\left(a_t\right) \cdot Ct_t $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;incorporating-multiple-reference-genes&#34;&gt;Incorporating multiple reference genes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selecting a relevant household gene is key to obtaining reliable results in qPCR, but depending on the circumstances, a single household reference may not be enough. Using multiple reference genes is then a good way to obtain more stable normalized Ct values. This involves taking the average value of the references and using it to normalize the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ -\Delta Ct_t = log_2(a_r) \cdot Ct_r - log_2(a_t) \cdot Ct_t $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We replace $log_2(a_r) \cdot Ct_r$ with the mean of multiple genes. This mean can be computed at the Cq and Ct value level, but this gives non-identical results. We use the Cq level (see also Hellemans et al, 2007, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2007-8-2-r19&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2007-8-2-r19&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ log_2(a_r) \cdot Ct_r \rightarrow  log_2 \left( \sum_i^{r \rightarrow n} a_i^{-Ct_i} \right)$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but the disadvantage of this approach is that highly expressed genes dominate the normalization. High values tend to have high variance at the Cq level, and hence they dominate the mean. Since this data is typically exponentially or log-normally distributed, we could use another estimate of average expression, such as log-average (see Dvinge &amp;amp; Bertone, 2009, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp578&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;10.1093/bioinformatics/btp578&lt;/a&gt;). Using the latter option gives a very intuitive solution to computation of normalized Ct data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ log_2(a_r) \cdot Ct_r \rightarrow  \frac{1}{n} \sum_i^{r \leftrightarrow n}  log_2\left( a_i \right) \cdot Ct_i $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $r \leftrightarrow n$ is the the number of reference genes we take the mean of, which each have there specific PCR efficiency factor $a_i$ and Ct value $Ct_i$. This solution is simply using the mean normalized Ct value of the reference genes to compute corrected  target Ct values. The final $-\Delta Ct_t$ then becomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ -\Delta Ct_t = \left[ \frac{1}{n} \sum_i^{r \leftrightarrow n}  log_2\left( a_i \right) \cdot Ct_i \right] - log_2\left(a_t\right) \cdot Ct_t $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;ddct&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;delta-delta-ct-formulae&#34;&gt;$-\Delta (\Delta) Ct$ formulae&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the $-\Delta Ct$ with multiple log-averaged household (reference) genes is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ -\Delta Ct_t = \left[ \frac{1}{n} \sum_i^{r \leftrightarrow n}  log_2\left( a_i \right) \cdot Ct_i \right] - log_2\left(a_t\right) \cdot Ct_t $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the $-\Delta\Delta Ct$ (i.e., target vs mock $Ct$, $\left(-\Delta Ct_t \right) - \left(-\Delta Ct_m \right)$) then follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ -\Delta\Delta Ct = \left[\left(\frac{1}{n} \sum_j^{s \leftrightarrow n}  log_2\left( a_j \right)  \cdot Ct_j \right) - log_2\left(a_m\right) \cdot Ct_m \right] $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ - \left[ \left( \frac{1}{n} \sum_i^{r \leftrightarrow n}  log_2\left( a_i \right) \cdot Ct_i \right) - log_2\left(a_t\right) \cdot Ct_t \right]$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $a_m$, $Ct_m$, $a_j$ and $Ct_j$ are the mock and mock reference values, and $a_t$, $Ct_t$, $a_i$ and $Ct_i$ are the target and target reference values, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;excel&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;delta-delta-ct-analysis-in-excel&#34;&gt;$-\Delta (\Delta) Ct$ analysis in Excel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation in Excel is pretty straight-forward if you use log-averaging:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;calibrate all of the raw Ct values by multiplying them with the $log_2$ of the PCR amplification efficiency for every gene on every plate:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;=LOG({PCR E},2)*{Ct}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the mean of the calibrated references (if more than one):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;=AVERAGE({calibrated Ct references})&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subtract the calibrated gene Ct value from the (average) calibrated reference Ct value to get the $-\Delta Ct$:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;={calibrated mean reference Ct}-{calibrated target Ct}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These values can be used to test for statistical significance between sample groups. The difference between a treatment and a mock group is then the $-\Delta\Delta Ct$ value:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;{normalized treatment} = {calibrated treatment mean reference Ct} - {calibrated treatment target Ct}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;{normalized mock} = {calibrated mock mean reference Ct} - {calibrated mock target Ct}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$-\Delta\Delta Ct$&lt;code&gt;={normalized mock} - {normalized treatment}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taqman efficiency calculation, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www3.appliedbiosystems.com/cms/groups/mcb_marketing/documents/generaldocuments/cms_040377.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Applied BioSystems Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dvinge &amp;amp; Bertone, 2009, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp578&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;10.1093/bioinformatics/btp578&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hellemans et al, 2007, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2007-8-2-r19&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2007-8-2-r19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dengue</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/project/dengue/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2017 16:57:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/project/dengue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dengue virus infection typically has mild symptomes, but can also cause hemorrhaegic fever and death in severe cases. Dengue has four serotypes and a secondary infection with a different serotype is associated with more severe symptomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project, we use - amongst others - transcriptome and proteome profiling to find markers that associate with severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity measures for antibodies: the adapted Shannon diversity index (ASDI)</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2017-11-20-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2017-11-20-diversity/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The diversity index is based on diversity concepts from ecology, where it is used to estimate the diversity of plant and animal life. You can think of the diversity index as a way to perform a weighted count of species. If you would like to compare the species diversity in different habitats, there are several ways of doing that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can count the number of different species present (but sensitive to &amp;lsquo;single&amp;rsquo; animals that are just &amp;lsquo;visiting&amp;rsquo; a habitat)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use the number of animals of which there are at least an &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; number (but difficult to determine &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;, e.g., 5 elephants is deemed more important for diversity than 5 ants)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a weighted average whereby animals are given more importance if there is many of them (that is the one we&amp;rsquo;re using!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diversity-measures-101&#34;&gt;Diversity measures 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different diversity measures. Each of them has a different range and all their values have different interpretations. To make life easy, these values can be represented as the number of responses of equal magnitude so as to provide an intuitive measure that everyone may understand. So a diversity of 5 means: &lt;em&gt;a diversity comparable to having 5 equally abundant species&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a highly cited (and highly recommended!) paper, &lt;a href=&#34;10.1111/j.2006.0030-1299.14714.x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;L. Jost, Oikos 2006&lt;/a&gt;) shows that many diversity measures map onto one another if you introduce a weighting factor that tunes the relative contribution of high- and low-abundant species to the final estimate of diversity. The final form of diversity equation looks scary, but is quite easy to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://henkjanvdh.github.io/img/diversityExample.png&#34; alt=&#34;Diversity measure example&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $D$ is the diversity measure of order $q$, $S$ is the number of species, and $p_i$ the proportion of animals from a specific species, expressed as a fraction.  Depending on how you weigh high-abundant vs low-abundant species (that would be parameter $q$), you obtain a different estimate of diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;interpretation&lt;/em&gt; of this index is diversity equivalent to that number of equally abundent species. For instance, a diversity of 3 means: 3 equally abundent species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adaptation-to-antibody-measurements&#34;&gt;Adaptation to antibody measurements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The index is adapted to be used for evaluating antibody measurements, i.e., fluorescence. To quantify diversity of responses, this index can be used. However, to down-weigh the influence of unprotective responses (i.e., those with a low fluorescence value), we include a parameter that sets the minimal level of what is considered an effective response: an &lt;em&gt;offset&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;anchor&lt;/em&gt; value to distinguish between background and real responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anchor value is taken along when the fractions of species are calculated. Please note that the anchor is not a cutoff, because the values below it are given less weight - but still taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://henkjanvdh.github.io/img/diversityAntigenArray.png&#34; alt=&#34;Diversity measure example for antigen arrays&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/freidl_sr16/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;our paper in Scientific Reports&lt;/a&gt; for more details. &lt;a href=&#34;https://images.nature.com/original/nature-assets/srep/2016/160208/srep20385/extref/srep20385-s1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Supplementary material S3&lt;/a&gt; contains the full derivation of the adapted index.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DC vaccination for HIV</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/project/hiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2017 11:23:31 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/project/hiv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To treat HIV-infected individuals, one approach is &lt;em&gt;therapeutic vaccination&lt;/em&gt; that aims to induce durable immunity by reactivating the individual&amp;rsquo;s immune system to HIV. Ideally, this would lead to viral control without taking combined anti-retroviral therapy (cART).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project, we examine several cohorts with -omics technology to try and understand the effect that these DC vaccinations have on vaccinated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcriptomic Analyses Reveal Differential Gene Expression of Immune and Cell Death Pathways in the Brains of Mice Infected with West Nile Virus and Chikungunya Virus</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/lim_fm17/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/lim_fm17/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of differentially expressed peptides in high-throughput proteomics data</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vanooijen_bb17/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vanooijen_bb17/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wat doet een virus?</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2016-11-21-virgo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/post/2016-11-21-virgo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Wat gebeurt er wanneer je geinfecteerd wordt door een virus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De afgelopen jaren heb ik geprobeerd deze vraag te beantwoorden in het kader van het &lt;a href=&#34;http://virgo.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;VIRGO project&lt;/a&gt;. De focus van dit project was om door middel van nieuwe &lt;em&gt;genomics&lt;/em&gt;-technologie virusinfecties in gastheren te bestuderen en bestrijden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KennisLink heeft een deel van dit onderzoek voor het voetlicht gebracht door onderzoekers te interviewen. Tijdens een van deze interviews heb ik verteld over ons onderzoek om &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nemokennislink.nl/publicaties/een-kakofonie-van-genactiviteit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;knokkelkoorts beter te begrijpen&lt;/a&gt;. Mijn collega Victor heeft verteld over ons werk &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nemokennislink.nl/publicaties/ziekenhuis-of-niet-je-genen-bepalen-het?q=virgo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;om de uitkomst van RSV infectie in jonge kinderen beter te voorspellen&lt;/a&gt;. De vraag was hier: welke kinderen een ernstige vorm van RSV zullen ontwikkelen en welke niet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;brochure&#34;&gt;Brochure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Een deel van het werk binnen het VIRGO project, waaronder de bovenstaande artikelen, is opgenomen in een &lt;a href=&#34;http://assets.kennislink.nl/system/files/000/239/550/original/VIRGO_boekje-dig_NED.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;brochure over het VIRGO project&lt;/a&gt; en maken deel uit van het KennisLink-thema &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nemokennislink.nl/thema/virussen-te-lijf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Virussen te lijf&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changes in heterosubtypic antibody responses during the first year of the 2009 A(H1N1) influenza pandemic</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/freidl_sr16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/freidl_sr16/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcriptome assists prognosis of disease severity in respiratory syncytial virus infected infants</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/jong_sr16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/jong_sr16/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DC immunotherapy in HIV-1 infection induces a major blood transcriptome shift</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/degoede_v15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/degoede_v15/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time since Onset of Disease and Individual Clinical Markers Associate with Transcriptional Changes in Uncomplicated Dengue</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_pntd15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_pntd15/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hyperferritinaemia in Dengue Virus Infected Patients Is Associated with Immune Activation and Coagulation Disturbances</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_pntd14/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_pntd14/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serum angiopoietin-2 and soluble VEGF receptor 2 are surrogate markers for plasma leakage in patients with acute dengue virus infection</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_jcv14/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_jcv14/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microbial Translocation Is Associated with Extensive Immune Activation in Dengue Virus Infected Patients with Severe Disease</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_pntd13/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2013 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/vandeweg_pntd13/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A better understanding of helper T cell differentiation using mathematical modelling and bioinformatics</title>
      <link>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/thesis_2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://henkjanvdh.github.io/publication/thesis_2010/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
